Register of the Pasternak Family Papers, 1877-2012
Hoover Institution Archives
- PASTERNAK TRUST ARCHIVES, 1877-2012; 118.0 boxes
  - LYDIA PASTERNAK SLATER FILE, 1917-1989; 70.0 boxes
    - Correspondence, 1918-1989 (Box 63-110)
      - General, 1918-1989 and undated (Box 65-110)
        - Zaguskin, Jacob (Yakov), 1936-1978 and undated (Box-folder 108: 1-5)
          - 1936-1961 (Box-folder 108: 1)
          - 1962-1965 (Box-folder 108: 2)
          - 1966-1967 (Box-folder 108: 3)
          - 1968-1970 (Box-folder 108: 4)
          - 1972-1978 and undated (Box-folder 108: 5)
        - Zaitsev, Boris, 1960-1962 (Box-folder 108: 6)
        - Zalydalsky(?), T., 1970
        - Zalz, Archie, 1960
        - Zamino’s. (see also: Khan, Irshad Ullah), 1969
        - Zamoyska, Hélène, 1961-1962, 1984
        - Zampa, Giorgio, 1968
        - Zbarskii, Boris, 1954-1946 (Box-folder 108: 7)
        - Zbinden, Hans, 1959
        - Zelikin, D., 1967-1968
        - Zernov, Nikolai, 1969-1971
        - Zhivova, Olimpiada, 1967
        - Zienko (Hindmann), Katie, 1980
        - Zinov’ev, Kirill, 1969
        - Zlias, Raphael K., 1974
        - Zullo, Leslie-Anne, 1984
        - Zveibach, Vladimir
        - Zweig, Marianne, undated
        - Unidentified, 1921-1986 and undated (Box-folder 108: 8-11; 109: 1-10; 110: 1-7)
          - 1921-1965 (Box-folder 108: 8)
          - 1966-1975 (Box-folder 108: 9)
          - 1976-1986 (Box-folder 108: 10)
          - undated (Box-folder 108: 11)
          - Arranged by first name, undated (Box-folder 109: 1-10; 110: 1-7, Folder 1-10)
      - Family correspondence, 1921-1989
        Arranged by first name, then chronologically by year.
        - General, letters from grandchildren, 1975-1989 (Box-folder 110: 8)
          Includes a letter and a postcard from Lydia to her children.
        - Pasternak, Aleksandr and Irina Vilyam (Aleksandr's wife), 1920s-1987 (Box-folder 111: 1-10; 112: 1-10; 113: 1-5)
          - Letters addressed to Leonid and Rosalia Pasternak and Josephine Pasternak and Lydia Pasternak Slater, 1920s-1930s (Box-folder 111: 1-6)
            - 1922-1927 (Box-folder 111: 1)
            - 1928-1929 and circa 1920s (Box-folder 111: 2)
            - 1930-1933 (Box-folder 111: 3)
            - 1934-1939 (Box-folder 111: 4)
            - circa 1930s (Box-folder 111: 5-6)
          - Letters addressed to Lydia Pasternak Slater, occasionally to Lydia Pasternak Slater and Josephine Pasternak, 1946-1989 (Box-folder 111: 7-10; 112: 1-10; 113: 1-5)
            Includes letters from Fedor and Anna, the children of Aleksandr Pasternak
            - 1946-1959 (Box-folder 111: 7)
            - 1960-1961 (Box-folder 111: 8)
            - 1962 (Box-folder 111: 9)
            - 1963-1964 (Box-folder 111: 10)
            - 1965 (Box-folder 112: 1)
            - 1966 (Box-folder 112: 2)
            - 1967 (Box-folder 112: 3)
            - 1968 (Box-folder 112: 4)
            - 1969 (Box-folder 112: 5)
            - 1960s (Box-folder 112: 6)
            - 1970 (Box-folder 112: 7)
            - 1971-1973 (Box-folder 112: 8)
            - 1974-1977 (Box-folder 112: 9)
            - 1978-1979 and 1970s (Box-folder 112: 10)
            - 1980 (Box-folder 113: 1-3)
            - 1980-1983 (Box-folder 113: 4)
            - 1983-1987 (Box-folder 113: 5)
              Letters from Irina Vilyam.
        - Pasternak, Boris, 1930, 1959 (Box-folder 113: 6)
          Includes a letter from Lydia (1930) and a copy of a letter from Boris (1959).
        - Pasternak, Elena Leonidovna, 1978-1980 (Box-folder 113: 7)
        - Pasternak, Evgeniĭ Borisovich and Elena Vladimirovna, 1962-1988 (Box-folder 113: 8-12; 114: 1-5)
          Includes letters from their children, Petr, Boris, and Elizaveta.
          - 1959-1961 (Box-folder 113: 8)
          - 1962-1963 (Box-folder 113: 9)
          - 1964-1965 (Box-folder 113: 10)
          - 1966-1967 (Box-folder 113: 11)
          - 1968-1969 (Box-folder 113: 12)
          - 1970-1972 (Box-folder 114: 1)
          - 1973-1975 (Box-folder 114: 2)
          - 1976-1979 (Box-folder 114: 3)
          - 1980-1984 (Box-folder 114: 4)
          - 1985-1988 (Box-folder 114: 5)
        - Pasternak, Evgeniia Vladimirovna, circa 1930, 1959-1964 (Box-folder 114: 6)
        - Pasternak, Josephine, 1920s-1980s (Box-folder 114: 7-12; 115: 1-3)
          - 1927-1929; 1920s (Box-folder 114: 7)
          - 1934-1936 (Box-folder 114: 8)
          - 1937-1938 (Box-folder 114: 9)
          - circa 1930s (Box-folder 114: 10-12)
          - 1955; 1959 (Box-folder 115: 1)
          - 1960-1969; 1960s (Box-folder 115: 2)
          - 1970s-1980s (Box-folder 115: 3)
        - Pasternak, Leonid Borisovich, 1961 and undated (Box-folder 115: 4)
        - Pasternak, Leonid Osipovich and Rosalia Isidorovna, 1925-1939 (Box-folder 115: 5-11; 116: 1-3)
          Includes letters addressed to Lydia Pasternak Slater and Josephine Pasternak.
          - 1925-1929 (Box-folder 115: 5)
          - 1929-1930 (Box-folder 115: 6)
          - 1931-1932 (Box-folder 115: 7)
          - 1933-1934 (Box-folder 115: 8)
          - 1935 (Box-folder 115: 9)
          - 1936 (Box-folder 115: 10-11)
            Includes letters to Eliot Slater.
          - 1937 (Box 116: 1-2)
          - 1938-1939 (Box-folder 116: 3)
        - Pasternak, Zinaida, 1960-1966 (Box-folder 116: 4)
        - Ramsay, Helen, 1937-1983 (Box-folder 116: 5)
        - Slater, Ann (Lisa) Pasternak, 1959-1986 and undated (Box-folder 116: 6)
        - Slater (Oppenheimer), Catherine (Rosa), 1950s-1986 (Box-folder 116: 7)
        - Slater, Eliot, 1935-1983. (Box-folder 116: 8)
          Includes one letter from Lydia, circa 1943.
        - Slater, Gilbert and Violet, 1937 (Box-folder 116: 9)
        - Slater, John and Sue, 1978 and undated
        - Slater, Michael, 1966-1988 and undated (Box-folder 116: 10)
        - Slater, Nicolas Pasternak and Maya, 1940s; 1951-1983 and 1980s
        - Slater, Renée, 1963-1986 (Box-folder 116: 11)
          Includes incoming and outgoing letters.
        - Slater, Shirley, 1960; 1963
        - Vilyam, Anna Nikolaevna (sister of Irina Vilyam), 1986-1988
    - Diaries, 1929-1989 (Box 117-122)
      Arranged by size, then by year.
      Include entries made by family members after Lydia's death.
      - 1929-1939 (Box 117)
      - 1936, 1941-1946, 1956-1957, 1959 (Box 118)
      - 1940, 1942, 1947-1955, 1958-1962, 1965, 1968-1969 (Box 119)
      - 1958, 1960, 1963-1967 (Box 120)
      - 1970-1975, 1977-1980, 1982-1983 (Box 121)
      - 1970, 1976, 1984-1989 (Box 122)
    - Subject file, 1961-1987 (Box-folder 123: 1-17)
      Arranged alphabetically by subject, then by year.
      - Art, 1961-1987 and undated (Box-folder 123: 1)
      - Ashmolean Museum, Oxford, 1974-1986 (Box-folder 123: 2)
      - Brodsky, Joseph, 1984 (Box-folder 123: 3)
      - Charity, 1970-1983 and undated (Box-folder 123: 4)
      - Conferences, 1976-1983 (Box-folder 123: 5)
      - Gallery Bookshop, undated (Box-folder 123: 6)
      - Graphikum Dr. H. Mock (see also: Correspondence: Graphikum), 1971-1984 and undated (Box-folder 123: 7)
      - Institute of Modern Russian Culture, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 123: 8)
      - Kemp, Harry, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 123: 9)
        Includes his poetry.
      - Leeds Russian Archives, 1983-1985 (Box-folder 123: 10)
      - Literature, 1966-1986 and undated (Box-folder 123: 11)
      - Music, 1964-1987 and undated (Box-folder 123: 12)
      - Oxford, John, 1985-1986 (Box-folder 123: 13)
      - Pasternak, Boris, publication of Poems of Boris Pasternak, 1962 (Box-folder 123: 14)
      - Pasternak, Leonid, exhibits, 1967, 1984 (Box-folder 123: 15)
      - Pasternak Trust (see also: Michael Slater file - Subject file - Pasternak Trust), 1985-1999 (Box-folder 123: 16)
      - Pushkin Club (see also: Correspondence - Pushkin Club), 1957-1978 and undated (Box-folder 123: 17)
      - Poetry and music, 1960-1984 (Oversize-box 172)
      - Rannit, Alexis, 1972-1985 (Box-folder 124: 1, Box 168)
      - Roniger, Boris, estate, 1965-1966 (Box-folder 124: 2)
      - S. Fisher Verlag, 1987 (Box-folder 124: 3)
      - Societies and associations, 1962-1987 and undated (Box-folder 124: 4)
      - Wilhelm Fink Verlag, 1978-1979 (Box-folder 124: 5)
      - Miscellanea, undated (Box-folder 124: 6)
    - Writings, 1930s-1980s
      - By Lydia Pasternak Slater, 1920s-1980s (Box 125-128, 169, Box-folder 129: 1-5)
        Includes her original works and translations from other languages. Holograph, typescripts, and published works. Also includes drawings (box 125, folder 1),
      - About Lydia Pasternak Slater, 1960, 1972 and undated (Box-folder 129: 6)
      - By others, undated (Box-folder 129: 7-10; 130: 1-9)
    - Photographs, 1946 and undated (Box-folder 130: 10-11)
      Prints depicting Lydia Pasternak Slater, Boris Pasternak's grave site, Pavel Ettinger, and Theo Goldenberg.
    - Printed matter, 1956-1994 and undated (Box-folder 131: 1-8)
    - Clippings, 1933, 1958-1989 and undated (Box 170)
  - LEONID AND ROSALIA PASTERNAK FILE, 1877-2012
    - Art, 1915-1994 and undated
      - Illustrations to Resurrection (photocopies), Moscow, 1915 (Box-folder 133: 4)
      - Portrait Album. Presse Dr. Selle and Co. A.G: Berlin, 1922 (Box 132)
      - Exhibits, 1928-1994
        - Catalogs, 1928-1994 (Box-folder 133: 1-2)
          Arranged alphabetically by title.
          - Allied Nation Art Exhibitions for the Forces, 1943
          - Drawings by Leonid Pasternak, 1890-1945. With an introduction by Josephine Pasternak. Ashmolean Museum, Oxford, 1990
          - L. N. Tolstoi v iskusstve i pechati, iublileinaia vystavka. Gosudarstvennaia Tret'iakovskaia galereia, 1928
          - Leonid Osipovich Pasternak, 1862-1945. Gosudarstvennaia Tret'akovskaia Galereia, 1979
          - Leonid Pasternak, 1862-1945, undated
          - Leonid Pasternak, 1862-1945. Crawford Center for the Arts, University of St. Andrews, 1978
          - Leonid Pasternak, 1862-1945. Oxford University Press, 1969
          - Leonid Pasternak, 1862-1945: A Russian Impressionist, Geri Richard Gallery, Taliesin Art Center, University College of Swansea, 1984
          - Leonid Pasternak, 1862-1945: Drawings, Pastels, Watercolours, Paintings. Maltazan Gallery, 1974
          - Leonid Pasternak, 1862-1945, Museum of Modern Art, Oxford, 1982-1983
          - Leonid Pasternak, Centenary Exhibition of Drawings and Paintings. Herbert Art Gallery and Museum, Coventry, 1962
          - Leonid Pasternak: Gift of Artist's Family, Museum of Private Collections at the Pushkin Museum of Fine Arts, 1994
          - 1962
          - Leonid Pasternak: The Russian Scenes, Pushkin House, 1958
          - Memorial Exhibition of Paintings and Drawings by Leonid Pasternak, 1862-1945, Ashmolean Museum, 1958
          - Musical Offering; Drawings, Pastels, Oils and Watercolours by Leonid Osipovich Pasternak, 1862-1945. Chamber Music Festival Exhibition at the Grave Art Gallery, Sheffield, 1994
          - Na solnechnom pliazhe, v iiune..., 2002
          - Russkie khudozhniki i muzyka. XIX - nachalo XX veka. Katalog vystavki "Dekabr'skie vechera,", 1981
        - Flyers and invitations (Box-folder 133: 3)
      - Artworks of Leonid Pasternak, photocopies, undated (Box 134)
      - Artworks by other artists collected by Leonid Pasternak, prints, undated (Box-folder 133: 5-6;, Oversize-box 168)
    - Biographical file, Rosalia Pasternak death and cremation records, 1939 (Box-folder 133: 7)
    - Correspondence, 1899-1945
      Divided into General and Family Correspondence; arranged alphabetically by last name, then chronologically by year
      - General, 1899-1945
        - General, 1939, 1942 (Box-folder 133: 8-9)
          - Condolence letters on the death of Rosalia Pasternak, 1939 (Box-folder 133: 8)
          - Greetings in honor of Leonid Pasternak's 80th birthday, 1942 (Box-folder 133: 9)
        - Abd-el Shahid, Hedy, 1944 (Box-folder 133: 10)
        - Birshtein, Vera, 1931
        - Block, A., 1942
        - British Broadcasting Corporation (includes broadcast transcript), 1944
        - Brodsky, Isaak Izrailevich (from Leonid Pasternak, a copy), undated
        - Butler, E.M., 1937, 1939
        - De Misès, 1932
        - Ettinger, Pavel, 1904; 1935-1939 (Box-folder 133: 11)
        - Harkevitch, Nina, 1933 (Box-folder 133: 12)
        - Hauptmann, Gerhard, 1930-1933 and undated (Box-folder 133: 13)
        - Hind, A., 1944 (Box-folder 133: 14)
        - Hossiason, Philippe, 1937
        - K., Hilde, 1942
        - Kraus, O., 1941
        - Lifshitz, Matilda, 1945
        - Maiskii, I. I. (draft letter from Leonid Pasternak), 1945
        - Rilke file, 1899-1902, 1926-1930 (Box-folder 135: 1)
          Includes letters from Rainer Maria Rilke with related correspondence; and two letters from Evgeniia Chernosvitova (R. M. Rilke's secretary) regarding Rilke's death, 1926 and 1927
          - Rilke Archiv, 1930
          - Rilke, Clara, 1929-1938
            Includes two postcards from Luisa Andreas Salomè, 1906 and 1931
          - Rilke, Rainer Maria, 1899-1902
          - Sieber Rilke, Ruth, 1932
        - Soviet Union, Posol’stvo (Great Britain)m, 1941 (Box-folder 135: 2)
        - Unidentified (three letters and twelve postcards), 1925-1939
      - Family correspondence, 1924-1941
        - General, 1924-1941 and undated
          - Kaufman, Berta, 1927-1928 and undated (Box-folder 135: 3)
          - Kaufman, Osip and Varvara, 1935-1937 and undated
          - Kaufman, Klara, undated
          - Pasternak, Aleksandr and Irina Vilyam, circa 1930s
          - Pasternak, Evgenii, 1931-1932 (Box-folder 135: 4)
          - Pasternak, Frederick (Fedor), 1924, 1930 (Box-folder 135: 5)
        - Pasternak, Josephine, 1920s-1939 (Box-folder 135: 6-12; 136: 1-8)
          - circa 1920s (Box-folder 135: 6-8)
          - 1924-1925 (Box-folder 135: 9)
          - 1926 (Box-folder 135: 10)
          - 1927-1929 (Box-folder 135: 11)
          - circa 1930s (Box-folder 135: 12; 136: 1-4)
          - 1930-1931 (Box-folder 136: 5)
          - 1932-1933 (Box-folder 136: 6)
          - 1934-1936 (Box-folder 136: 7)
          - 1936-1939 (Box-folder 136: 8)
        - Slater, Lydia Pasternak, 1924-1941 and undated. (Box-folder 136: 9-10; 137: 1-11)
          Includes letters from Eliot Slater.
          - 1924-1928 (Box-folder 136: 9)
          - 1929 (Box-folder 136: 10)
          - 1930 (Box-folder 137: 1)
          - 1931 (Box-folder 137: 2)
          - 1932 (Box-folder 137: 3)
          - 1933-1934 (Box-folder 137: 4)
          - 1935 (Box-folder 137: 5)
          - 1936 (Box-folder 137: 6-8)
          - 1937 (Box-folder 137: 9-10)
          - 1938-1939, 1941 and undated (Box-folder 137: 11)
        - Slater, Violet and Gilbert, 1935-1937 (Box-folder 137: 12)
    - Writings, 1932 and undated
      - "Leonid Pasternak" by Max Osborn, pp. 1-56; 81-88; 97-112. Galley, incomplete, 1932 (Box-folder 138: 1)
        - Excerpts from the Max Osborn book (Box-folder 138: 2-6)
          - "Auszüge aus Meine Autobiographie." Typescript and galley (Box-folder 138: 2)
          - "Begegnungen mit Lovis Corinth." Typescript and galley (Box-folder 138: 3)
          - "Begegnungen mit Rainer Maria Rilke." Typescript and galley (Box-folder 138: 4)
          - "Begegnungen mit Tolstoi." Holograph (not in hand of Leonid Pasternak), typescript, and galley (Box-folder 138: 5-6)
        - Fragments and loose pages. Galley (Box-folder 138: 7-8)
        - Published excerpts (Box-folder 138: 9)
        - Miscellanea (Box-folder 138: 10)
      - Reminiscences, undated
        - Untitled typescript, photocopy (Box-folder 139: 1-4)
        - Working papers (Box-folder 139: 5)
      - "Pervyi pogrom v Odesse." Typescript, undated (Box-folder 139: 6)
      - "Vstrechi s Tolstym." Typescript, undated (Box-folder 139: 7)
      - "Zapisi raznykh let,", undated
        - Original typescript with holograph corrections, undated (Box-folder 139: 8-12; 140: 1-2)
        - Typescript (photocopy) (Box-folder 140: 3-7)
    - Writings about Leonid and Rosalia Pasternak, 1904-1908, 1945-1996
      - Rosalia Kaufman-Pasternak, 1904, 1908, 1963 and undated (Box-folder 140: 8)
        Includes typed copies of report about Rosalia Pasternak concerts published in Russkie vedomosti No. 17, 1904 and No. 257, 1908.
        - Concerts, reports. Typed copy, 1904, 1908
        - Levitsky, Serge, "Rose Koffmann-Pasternak: La mère du poète," Slavic and East European Studies. Clipping, 1963
        - Pasternak, Josephine, reminiscences. Typescript draft, undated
        - "A. L. Pasternak: Souvenirs sur R. I. Kaufmann - Pasternak" (extracts). Typescript (draft), undated
        - A. L. Pasternak, "Iz vospominaii o R. I. Kaufman-Pasternak." Typescript, draft, undated
      - Leonid Pasternak, 1945-1996
        - General, 1945-1996 (Box-folder 140: 9)
          - Hind, A. M., "Leonid Pasternak: An Appreciation by A. M. Hind," The Studio magazine, November, p. 151, 1945-1996
          - Prithwindranath Mukhopadhya, "Pasternak:The Painter (Je Pasternak Chhabi Ankten)," Desh magazine [In Bengali], 1962`
          - Buckman, David, "The Unknown Pasternak," The Antique Collector, pp. 12-15,9, 1974 December
          - Holman, Michael J. de K., "Illustrating the English Version of Resurrection: Leonid Pasternak's Correspondence with Louise Maude," Slavonica, vol. 2, no 1, 1995-1996
        - Salys, Rimgaila (Rima), "Leonid Pasternak, the Russian Years: 1875-1921," a critical study and catalog. Typescript with Josephine Pasternak's notes, 1987 (Box-folder 141: 1-4)
    - Writings by others, 1986
      - Salys, Rimgaila, "Signs on the Road of Life: The Death of Ivan Il'ich." Typescript, 1986 (Box-folder 141: 5)
      - Miscellanea (Box-folder 141: 6)
    - Books collected by Leonid Pasternak, 1926-1936 1926-1936 (Box-folder 141: 8-9)
    - Book of clippings. In various languages, 1877-1884 (Box 134)
    - Clippings, 1941-1988, 2012 and undated (Oversize-box 171)
    - Memorabilia, undated (Box-folder 141: 10)
    - Photographs, 1930s, 1980s and undated (Box-folder 141: 11-12)
    - Printed matter, 1942-1947 (Box-folder 131: 9)
  - BORIS PASTERNAK FILE, 1914-2013
    - Biographical file, certificate of the Nobel Prize Award, 1964 (Box 168)
    - Correspondence, 1921-1960
      - Letters to parents and sisters, 1921-1960
        - Holographs, 1921-1960 (Box-folder 142: 1-7)
          - 1921-1928 (Box-folder 142: 1)
            Includes occasional letters from Evgeniia Pasternak.
          - 1929-1932 (Box-folder 143: 2)
          - 1933-1936 (Box-folder 143: 3)
          - 1937-1940 (Box-folder 143: 4)
          - 1941-1948 (Box-folder 143: 5)
            Includes essay "O Shopene" by Boris Pasternak with his holograph annotations and a letter to S. Schimanski.
          - 1956-1958 (Box-folder 143: 6)
            Includes New Year greetings from Olga Ivinskaia and Irina Emel'ianova and a letter from George Nivat.
          - 1959-1960 (Box-folder 143: 7)
      - Letters to Western correspondents collected by Lydia Pasternak Slater. Mostly photocopies, 1959-1961 (Box-folder 143: 1-8)
        Includes list of correspondents compiled by Christopher Barnes (box 143, folder 1) and Lydia's appeal to them for return of Boris Pasternak's letters to them, with related correspondence.
      - Miscellaneous letters.Typescripts, 1922, 1947, 1958 (Box-folder 143: 9-10)
        Includes excerpts from letters to Selma Rauoff and Marina Baranovich and selected letters from Marina Tsvetaeva.
    - Musical scores by Boris Pasternak, undated (Oversize-box 168)
    - Writings, 1914-1959
      Arranged chronologically by year.
      - Various poems. Holograph and typescript, 1914-1916, 1956 (Box-folder 144: 1)
      - "Bezliub'e." Glava iz povesti. Typescript, 1918 (Box-folder 144: 2)
      - "Dialog." In Russian (typescript, photocopy) and English (typescript), 1918
      - "Pis'ma iz Tuly." Holograph, 1918
      - "Tri glavy iz povesti." Typescript, 1922
      - "Spektorskii." Glava pervaia. Typescript, 1925
      - "Okhrannaia gramota." Typescript and poster, 1929 (Box-folder 144: 3, Box 168)
        - Vspupitel'nyi ocherk. Typescript, 1929
        - Posleslovie. Typescript (three copies), 1929, 1931
          One copy includes a poem, entitled "Strelochke," dated 1921
      - Dve ballady. Holograph, 1930 (Box-folder 144: 3)
      - "Slepaia krasavitsa." Typescript (photocopy), 1942 (Box-folder 144: 4)
      - La bellezza cieca. Unidentified publication of the play "Slepaia krasavitsa" translated into Italian, with the introduction by Giancarlo Vigorelli. Photocopy, undated (Box-folder 144: 5)
      - "Shopen," essay. Typescipt, circa 1945 (Box-folder 144: 6)
      - "Stat'ia o Shopene," essay, 1945
        Includes two versions of the essay.
      - Predislovie k shekspirovskim perevodam. Typescipt, 1946
      - "Rozhdestvenskaia zvezda." Typescipt, 1947
      - "A Translator's Note," The New Republic, p. 21, 1958 December 29
      - "Nobelevskaia premiia." Holograph (photocopy), 1959
      - Doktor Zhivago
        - "Doktor Zhivago: Kartiny poluvekovogo obikhoda." V dvukh knigakh. Typescript, 1948 (Box-folder 144: 7)
          Chast' Pervaia. "Piatichasovyi skoryi."
        - "Doktor Zhivago." Kniga pervaia i vtoraia, undated (Box 145-146)
          Bound typescript in two volumes received by Lydia Pasternak Slater from Georgy Katkov. Includes Ann Pasternak Slater's note.
        - "Fragmenty romana," Collins and Harvill Press. Typescript (photocopy), 1973 (Box-folder 144: 7)
        - "Doktor Schiwago" von Boris Pasternak, S. Fischer-Verlag, Ausgabe, pp. 513-520. Photocopy, 1958 (Box-folder 144: 8)
        - "The poems of Doctor Zhivago." Translated from Russian by Eugene M. Kayden. Hallmark Crown Editions, 1971 (Oversize-box 168)
      - "Was ist der Mensch?" interview, in unidentified periodical. Photocopy, undated (Box-folder 147: 1)
      - Translation of Titsian Tabidze. Holograph (not in hand of Boris Pasternak), undated
      - "Boris Pasternak: Les lettres du poète persécuté à ses amis géorgiens", Le Figaro Litteraire, no. 1171, pp. 12-14, 1968 14-20 October
      - "Boris Pasternak i G. Kozintsev: Pis'ma o Gamlete. Publication (photocopy) in unidentified periodical, circa 1974
    - Translations of Boris Pasternak writings, 1944-1986 (Box-folder 147: 2-4)
      Arranged alphabetically by name of translator.
      - Bastaan, Marijke, 1968 (Box-folder 147: 2)
        Translated into Dutch.
      - Bowra, C. M., circa 1948
      - Brown, Alec, 1958 and undated
      - Coleman, John, undated
      - Fallen, J. E., undated
      - Kline, George, circa 1960 (Box-folder 147: 3)
      - McKane, Richard, undated
        Includes a letter to Evgenii Pasternak of (1989).
      - Marshall, Herbert, 1986
      - Nenham, Richard. Typescript and clippings, circa 1960
      - Preussfreund, Nina, 1969 and undated
      - Reavey, George, undated (Box-folder 147: 4)
      - Slater, Nicolas Pasternak, 1965, 1970
      - Szamuely, Helen, undated
      - Warrlich, Victoria, circa 1959
        Includes a cover letter from Walter Philipp.
      - Williams, Allan Morray, undated
        Includes his translations of Konstantin Simonov and Vladimir Mayakovsky.
      - Unidentified, circa 1944 and undated
    - Writings about Boris Pasternak, critical reviews and biographical materials, 1956-2010 (Box-folder 147: 5-9)
      - Abashev, V.V., "Puteshestvie s doktorom Zhivago: Boris Pasternak v Permskom krae," Sankt-Peterburg. Photocopy, 2010 (Box-folder 147: 5)
      - Alekhin, Iurii, "On pereshel zemli granitsy," Krugozor, no. 2, pp. 12-13. Photocopy, 1990
      - Anning, Nicolas, "The Poet." Typescript, undated
      - Barnes, Christopher, 1983 and undated (Box-folder 147: 6)
        - "Biography, Autobiography, and Pasternak's Life." Typescript, undated